Chapter 24 As I rose and dressed, I thought over what had happened,
and wondered if it were a dream.
I could not be certain of the reality till I had seen Mr. Rochester again,
and heard him renew his words of love and promise.
While arranging my hair, I looked at my face
in the glass, and felt it was no longer plain.
There was hope in its aspect and life in its color, and my eyes seemed as if they
had beheld the fount of fruition, and borrowed beams from the lustrous ripple.
I had often been unwilling to look at my master, because I feared he could not be
pleased at my look, but I was sure I might lift my face
to his now, and not cool his affection by its expression.
I took a plain but clean and light sum -address from my drawer and put it on.
It seemed no attire had ever so well become me,
because none had I ever worn in so blissful a mood.
I was not surprised when I ran down into the hall, to see that a brilliant June
morning had succeeded to the tempest of the night, and to feel through the open
glass door the breathing of a fresh and fragrant breeze.
Nature must be gladsome when I was so happy.
A beggar woman and her little boy, pale ragged objects both, were coming up
the walk, and I ran down and gave them all the money I happened to have in my purse.
Some three or four shillings, good or bad, they must partake of my jubilee.
The rook's cord, and believe the bird's sang, but nothing
was so merry or so musical as my own rejoicing heart.
Mrs. Fairfax surprised me by looking out of the window with a sad countenance and
saying gravely, Miss Air, will you come to breakfast?
During the meal she was quiet and cool, but I could not understive her then.
I must wait for my master to give explanations and so must she.
I ate what I could, and then I hastened upstairs.
I met Adele leaving the schoolroom.
Where are you going?
It is time for lessons.
Mr. Rochester has sent me away to the nursery.
Where is he?
In there, pointing to the apartment she had left, and I went in.
And there he stood.
Come and bid me good morning, said he.
I gladly advanced, and it was not merely a cold word now, or even a shake of the hand
that I received, but an embrace and a kiss.
It seemed natural.
It seemed genial to be so well loved, so caressed by him.
Jane, you look blooming and smiling and pretty, said he.
Truly pretty this morning.
Is this my pale little elf?
Is this my mustard seed?
This little sunny-faced girl with the dimpled cheek and rosy lips, the satin
smooth hazel hair, and the radiant hazel eyes?
I had green eyes, reader, but you must excuse the mistake.
For him they were new-dyed, I suppose.
It is Jane air, sir.
Soon to be Jane Rochester.
He added, in four weeks, Janet, not a day more.
Do you hear that?
I did.
And I could not quite comprehend it.
It made me giddy.
The feeling, the announcement sent through me, was something stronger than was
consistent with joy, something that smote and stunned.
It was, I think, almost fear.
You blushed, and now you are white, Jane.
What is that for?
Because you gave me a new name.
Jane Rochester, and it seems so strange.
Yes, Mrs. Rochester, said he.
Young Mrs. Rochester.
Fairfax Rochester's girl, bride.
It can never be, sir.
It does not sound likely.
Human beings never enjoy complete happiness in this world.
I was not born for a different destiny to the rest of my species.
To imagine such a lot beforeling me as a fairytale, a
daydream, which I can and will realize, I shall begin today.
This morning, I wrote to my banker in London, to send me certain jewels he has
in his keeping, heirlooms for the ladies of Thornfield.
In a day or two, I hope to pour them into your lap, for every privilege,
every attention shall be yours, that I would accord a peer's daughter,
if about to marry her.
Oh, sir, never rain jewels.
I don't like to hear them spoken of.
Jewels for Jane heir sounds unnatural and strange.
I would rather not have them.
I will myself put the diamond chain round your neck, and the circuit on your
forehead, which it will become, for nature at least, has stamped her
patent of nobility on this brow, Jane, and I will clasp the bracelets on
these fine wrists, and load these fairy -like fingers with rings.
No, no, sir, think of other subjects, and
speak of other things, and in another strain.
Don't address me as if I were a beauty.
I am your plain, quaker-ish, governess.
You are a beauty in my eyes, and a beauty just after the desire of my heart,
delicate and aerial.
Puny and insignificant, you mean.
You are dreaming, sir, or you are sneering for God's sake, don't be ironical.
I will make the world acknowledge you a beauty, too.
He went on.
While I really became uneasy at the strain he had adopted, because I felt he was
either deluding himself for trying to delude me.
I will attire my Jane in satan and lace, and she shall have roses in her hair,
and I will cover the head I love best with a priceless veil.
And then you won't know me, sir.
And I shall not be your Jane heir any longer, but an
ape in a Harlequin's jacket, a jay in borrowed plumes.
I would as soon see you, Mr. Rochester, tricked out in
stage trappings as myself clad in a court-lady's robe.
And I don't call you handsome, sir, though I love you most dearly,
far too dearly to flatter you, don't flatter me.
He pursued his theme, however, without noticing my deprecation.
This very day I shall take you in the carriage to
Milcoat, and you must choose some dresses for yourself.
I told you we shall be married in four weeks.
The wedding is to take place quietly in the church down
below Yonder, and then I shall waft you away at once to town.
After a brief stay there, I shall bear my treasure to regions near the sun,
to French vineyards and Italian plains, and she shall
see whatever is famous in old story and in modern record.
She shall taste, too, of the life of cities, and she shall
learn to value herself by just comparison with others.
Shall I travel, and with you, sir?
You shall sojourn at Paris, Rome, and Naples, at Florence, Venice, and Vienna.
All the ground I have wandered over shall be retrodden by you.
Wherever I stamped my hoof, your silph's foot shall step also.
Ten years since, I flew through Europe half-mad,
with disgust, hate, and rage as my companions.
Now I shall revisit it, healed and cleansed, with a very angel as my comforter.
I laughed at him as he said this.
I am not an angel, I asserted, and I will not be one till I die.
I will be myself.
Mr. Rochester, you must neither expect nor exec anything celestial of me.
For you will not get it, any more than I shall
get it of you, which I do not at all anticipate.
What do you anticipate of me?
For a little while, you will perhaps be as you are now, a very little while,
and then you will turn cool, and then you will be capricious, and then you will be
stern, and I shall have much ado to please you.
But when you get well used to me, you will perhaps like me again.
Like me I say, not love me.
I suppose your love will effervesce in six months or less.
I have observed in books written by men, that period
assigned as the farthest to which a husband's ardor extends.
Yet, after all, as a friend and companion, I hope
never to become quite distasteful to my dear master.
Distasteful, and like you again, I think I shall like you again,
and yet again, and I will make you confess I do not only like, but love you,
with truth, fervor, constancy.
Yet are you not capricious, sir?
To women who please me only by their faces, I am the very
devil when I find out they have neither the souls nor hearts.
When they open to me a perspective of flatness, triviality, and perhaps in
versility, coarseness, and ill-temper, but to the clear eye and eloquent tongue,
to the soul made of fire, and the character that bends but does not break,
at once supple and stable, tractable and consistent, I am ever tender and true.
How do you ever experience such a character, sir?
Did you ever love such in one?
I love it now, but before me, if I indeed, in any respect
come up to your difficult standard, I never met your likeness.
Jane, you please me, and you master me.
You seem to submit, and I like the sense of play and see you impart, and while I am
twining the soft, silken skein' round my
finger, it sends a thrill up my arm to my heart.
I am influenced, conquered, and the influence is sweeter than I can express,
and the conquest I undergo has a witchery beyond any triumph I can win.
Why do you smile, Jane?
What does that inexplicable, that uncanny turn of countenance mean?
I was thinking, sir.
You will excuse the idea it was in voluntary.
I was thinking of Hercules and Samson with their charmers.
You were, you little elfish, hush, sir.
You don't talk very wisely just now, any more than those gentlemen acted very wisely.
However, had they been married, they would no doubt by their severity as
husbands have made up for their softness as suitors, and so will you, I fear.
I wonder how you will answer me a year hence?
Should I ask a favor it does not suit your convenience or pleasure to grant?
Ask me something now, Janet, the least thing.
I desire to be entreated.
Indeed, I will, sir.
I have my petition already.
Speak.
But if you look up and smile with that countenance, I shall swear concession
before I know to what, and that will make a fool of me.
Not at all, sir.
I ask only this.
Don't send for the jewels, and don't crown me with roses.
You might as well put a border of gold lace around
that plain pocket hankerchief you have there.
I might as well guild refined gold.
I know it.
Your request is granted then, for the time.
I will remind the order I dispatched to my
banker, but you have not yet asked for anything.
You have prayed a gift to be withdrawn.
Try again.
Well then, sir.
Have the goodness to gratify my curiosity, which is much peaked on one point.
He looked disturbed.
What?
He said hastily.
Curiosity is a dangerous petition.
It is well I have not taken a vow to accord every request, but there can be no
danger in complying with this, sir.
utter it, Jane.
But I wish that instead of a mere inquiry into
perhaps a secret, it was a wish for half my estate.
Now, King Ahasuerus, what do I want with half your estate?
Do you think I am a due usurer?
Seeking good investment in land?
I would much rather have all your confidence.
You will not exclude me from your confidence if you admit me to your heart.
You are welcome to all my confidence that is worth having, Jane.
But for God's sake, don't desire a useless burden.
Don't long for poison.
Don't turn out a downright eve on my hands.
Why not, sir?
You have just been telling me how much you like to be
conquered and how pleasant over persuasion is to you.
Don't you think I had better take advantage of the confession and begin in
coax and in treat, even cry and be sulky if
necessary for the sake of mere essay of my power?
I dare you to any such experiment, encroach, presume, and the game is up.
Is it, sir?
You soon give in, how stern you look now.
Your eyebrows have become as thick as my finger, and your forehead resembles what
in some very astonishing poetry I once saw styled a blue piled thunder loft.
That will be your married look, sir, I suppose.
If that will be your married look, I, as a Christian, will soon give up the
notion of consorting with a mere sprite or salamander.
But what had you to ask, thing, out with it?
There, you are less than civil now, and I like
rudeness a great deal better than flattery.
I had rather be a thing than an angel.
This is what I have to ask.
Why did you take such pains to make me believe you wish to marry Miss Ingram?
Is that all?
Thank God it is no worse.
And now he unknit his black brows, looked down, smiling at me, and stroked my
hair, as if well pleased at seeing a danger averted.
I think I may confess, he continued, even although
I should make you a little indignant, Jane.
And I have seen what a fire spirit you can be when you are indignant.
You glowed in the cool moonlight last night, when you mutinyed against fate,
and claimed your rank as my equal.
Janet, by the by, it was you who made me the offer.
Of course I did, but to the point of you please sir, Miss Ingram.
Well, I feigned courtship of Miss Ingram, because I wish to render you as madly in
love with me as I was with you, and I knew jealousy would be the best ally
I could call in for the furtherance of that end.
Excellent, now you are small, not one wit bigger than the end of my little finger.
It was a burning shame and a scandalous disgrace to act in that way.
Did you think nothing of Miss Ingram's feelings, sir?
Her feelings are concentrated in one, pride, and that needs humbling.
Were you jealous, Jane?
Never mind, Mr. Rochester.
It is in no way interesting to you to know that.
Answer me truly once more.
Do you think Miss Ingram will not suffer from your dishonest cockatry?
Won't she feel forsaken and deserted?
Impossible.
When I told you how she, on the contrary, deserted me, the idea of my insolvency
cooled or rather extinguished her flame in a moment.
You have a curious, designing mind, Mr. Rochester.
I'm afraid your principles on some points are eccentric.
My principles were never trained, Jane.
They may have grown a little awry for want of attention.
Once again, seriously, may I enjoy the great good that has been vouchsafed to me,
without fearing that anyone else is suffering
the bitter pain I myself felt a while ago.
That you may, my good little girl.
There is not another being in the world has the same pure love for me as yourself.
For I lay that pleasant action to my soul, Jane, a belief in your affection.
I turn my lips to the hand that lay on my shoulder.
I loved him very much.
More than I could trust myself to say.
More than words had power to express.
Ask something more, he said presently.
It is my delight to be entreated and to yield.
I was again ready with my request.
Communicate your intentions to Mrs. Fairfax, sir.
She saw me with you last night in the hall and she was shocked.
Give her some explanation before I see her again.
It pains me to be misjudged by so good a woman.
Go to your room and put on your bonnet, he replied.
I mean you to accompany me to Milkut this morning, and while you prepare for the
drive, I will enlighten the old lady's understanding.
Did she think Janet, you had given the world for love and considered it well lost?
I believe she thought I had forgotten my station and yours, sir.
Station.
Your station is in my heart and on the next of
those who would insult you now or hereafter.
Go.
I was soon dressed, and when I heard Mr. Rochester quit, Mrs. Fairfax's parlour,
I hurried down to it.
The old lady had been reading her morning portion of scripture.
The lesson for the day, her Bible lay open
before her, and her spectacles were upon it.
Her occupation, suspended by Mr. Rochester's announcement, seemed now forgotten.
Her eyes fixed on the blank wall opposite, expressed the
surprise of a quiet mind stirred by unwanted tidings.
Seeing me, she roused herself.
She made a sort of effort to smile and framed a few words of congratulation.
But the smile expired, and the sentence was abandoned unfinished.
She put up her spectacles, shut the Bible, and pushed her chair back from the table.
I feel so astonished, she began.
I hardly know what to say to you, Miss Ayer.
I have surely not been dreaming, have I?
Sometimes I have fall asleep when I'm sitting
alone and fancy things that have never happened.
It has seemed to me more than once when I've been in a dose, that my dear husband,
who died 15 years since, has come in and sat down beside me, and that I've even
heard him call me by my name, Alice, as he used to do.
Now, can you tell me whether it is actually true
that Mr. Rochester has asked you to marry him?
Don't laugh at me, but I really thought he came in here five
minutes ago and said that in a month you would be his wife.
He has said the same thing to me, I replied.
He has.
Do you believe him?
Have you accepted him?
Yes.
She looked at me bewildered.
I could never have thought it.
He is a proud man.
All the Rochester's were proud, and his father at least liked money.
He too has always been called careful.
He means to marry you.
He tells me so.
She surveyed my whole person.
In her eyes, I read that they had their found
no charm, powerful enough to solve the enigma.
It passes me, she continued, but no doubt it is true since you say so.
How it will answer, I cannot tell.
I really don't know.
A quality of position and fortune is often advisable in such
cases, and there are 20 years of difference in your ages.
He might almost be your father.
No, indeed Mrs. Fairfax exclaimed I, nettleed.
He is nothing like my father.
No one who saw us together would suppose it for an instant.
Mr. Rochester looks as young and is as young as some men at five and twenty.
Is it really for love he is going to marry you?
She asked.
I was so hurt by her coldness and skepticism that the tears rose to my eyes.
I'm sorry to grieve you pursued the widow, but you are so young and so little
acquainted with men, I wished to put you on your guard.
It is an old saying that all is not gold that glitters.
And in this case, I do fear there will be something
found to be different to what either you or I expect.
Why?
Am I a monster?
I said.
Is it impossible that Mr. Rochester should have a sincere affection for me?
No, you are very well, and much improved of late, and Mr. Rochester, head of his.
There are times when, for your sake, I have been a little uneasy at his marked
preference, and have wished to put you on your guard, but
I did not like to suggest even the possibility of wrong.
I knew such an idea would shock, perhaps offend you, and you were so
discrete and so thoroughly modest and sensible.
I hoped you might be trusted to protect yourself.
Last night, I cannot tell you what I suffered when I sought all over the house
and could find you nowhere, nor the master either, and then, at twelve o'clock,
saw you come in with him.
Well, never mind that now, I interrupted impatiently.
It is enough that all was right.
I hope all will be right in the end, she said,
but believe me, you cannot be too careful.
Try and keep Mr. Rochester at a distance.
Distrust yourself as well as him.
Gentleman in his station are not accustomed to marry their governesses.
I was growing truly irritated.
Happily, Adele ran in.
Let me go.
Let me go to Milkut, too, she cried.
Mr. Rochester won't, though there is so much room in the new carriage,
beg him to let me go, Mademoiselle.
That I will, Adele, and I hastened away with her, glad to quit my gloomy monatrous.
The carriage was ready.
They were bringing it round to the front, and my master was pacing the pavement,
pilot following him backwards and forwards.
Adele may accompany us.
May she not, sir.
I told her no.
I'll have no brats.
I'll have only you.
Do let her go, Mr. Rochester.
If you please, it would be better.
Not it.
She will be a restraint.
He was quite preemptory, both in look and voice.
The chill of Mrs. Fairfax's warnings, and the damp of her doubts were upon me,
something of unsubstantiality and uncertainty, had beset my hopes.
I half lost the sense of power over him.
I was about mechanically to obey him, without further remonstrance.
But as he helped me into the carriage, he looked at my face.
What is the matter, he asked?
All the sunshine is gone.
Do you really wish the band to go?
Will it annoy you if she is left behind?
I would far rather she went, sir.
Then off for your bonnet, and back like a flash of lightning cried he to Adele.
She obeyed him with what speed she might.
After all, a single morning's interruption will not matter much, said he,
when I mean shortly to claim you, your thoughts, conversation and company for life.
Adele, when lifted in, commenced kissing me, by way
of expressing her gratitude for my intercession.
She was instantly stowed away into a corner on the other side of him.
She then peeped round to where I sat, so stern a neighbour was too restrictive.
To him, in his present, fractious mood, she dared whisper no observations,
nor ask of him any information.
Let her come to me, I entreated.
She will perhaps trouble you, sir.
There is plenty of room on this side.
He handed her over as if she had been a lap dog.
I'll send her to school yet, he said, but now he was smiling.
Adele heard him, and asked if she was to go to school, saw Mademoiselle.
Yes, he replied.
Absolutely saw Mademoiselle.
For I am to take Mademoiselle to the moon, and there I shall seek a cave in one of
the white valleys among the volcano tops, and Mademoiselle shall live with me there,
and only me.
She will have nothing to eat, you will starve her, observed Adele.
I shall gather Mademoiselle for her morning and night, the plains and
hillsides in the moon are bleached with Mademoiselle.
She will want to warm herself, what will she do for a fire?
Fire rises out of the lunar mountains.
When she is called, I'll carry her up to a
peak and lay her down on the edge of a crater.
Oh, curly Sarah Mel, poo comfortable, and her clothes they will wear out.
How can she get new ones?
Mr. Rochester professed to be puzzled.
Him said he, What would you do, Adele?
Cuddle your brains for an expedient.
How would a white or a pink cloud answer for a gown, do you think?
And one could cut a pretty enough scarf out of a rainbow.
She is far better as she is, concluded Adele after musing some time.
Besides, she would get tired of living with only you in the moon.
If I were Mademoiselle, I would never consent to go with you.
She has consented, she has pledged her word.
But you can't get her there, there's no road to the moon, it is all air,
and neither you nor she can fly.
Adele, look at that field.
We were now outside Thornfield gates, and bowling lightly along the smooth road
to Milcoat, where the dust was well laid by the thunderstorm, and where the low
hedges and lofty timbetries on each side glistened green and rain refreshed.
In that field Adele, I was walking late one evening about a fortnight since,
the evening of the day you helped me to make hay in the orchard meadows,
and as I was tired with raking swathes, I sat down to rest me on a style,
and there I took out a little book and a pencil, and began to write about a
misfortune that befell me long ago, and a wish I had for happy days to come.
I was writing away very fast, though daylight was fading from the leaf,
when something came up the path and stopped two yards of me.
I looked at it, it was a little thing with a veil of gossamer on its head,
I beckoned it to come near me, it stood soon at my knee.
I never spoke to it, and it never spoke to me in words, but I read its eyes,
and it read mine, and our speechless colloquy was to this effect, it was a
fairy, and come from elf land it said, and its errand was to make me happy.
I must go with it out of the common world, to a lonely place, such as the moon,
for instance, and it nodded its head towards her horn, rising over hay hill.
It told me of the alabaster cave and silver veil where we might live.
I said I should like to go, but reminded it as you did me, that I had no wings to fly.
Oh, return the fairy, that does not signify, here is a talisman will remove
all difficulties, and she held out a pretty gold ring.
Put it, she said, on the fourth finger of my left hand, and I am yours, and you are
mine, and we shall leave earth and make our own heaven yonder.
She nodded again at the moon, the ring Adele is in my breaches pocket under the
disguise of a sovereign, but I mean soon to change it to a ring again.
But what has Mamoiselle to do with it?
I don't care for the fairy, you said it was Mamoiselle you would take to the moon.
Mamoiselle is a fairy, he said, whispering mysteriously, whereupon I told
her not to mind his bad inage, and she, on her part, evinced a fund of
genuine French scepticism, denominating Mr. Rochester on Vrymenta, and assuring
him that she made no account whatever of his contife, and
that du rest in the evade part de Faise équand m'élyanevate.
She was sure they would never appear to him, nor ever
give him rings, or offer to live with him in the moon.
The hour spent at Milcoat was a somewhat harrassing one to me.
Mr. Rochester obliged me to go to a certain silk warehouse.
There, I was ordered to choose half a dozen dresses.
I hated the business.
I begged leave to defer it.
No, it should be gone through with now.
By dint of entreaties expressed in energetic
whispers, I reduced the half dozen to two.
These, however, he vowed he would select himself.
With anxiety, I watched his eye rove over the gay stores.
He fixed on a rich silk of the most brilliant amethyst die, and a superb pink satin.
I told him in a new series of whispers, that he might
as well buy me a gold gown and a silver bonnet at once.
I should certainly never venture to wear his choice, with infinite difficulty,
for he was stubborn as a stone.
I persuaded him to make an exchange in favour
of a sober black satin and pearl grey silk.
It might pass for the present, he said, but
he would yet see me glittering like a partair.
Glad was I to get him out of the silk warehouse, and then out of a jewelers shop.
The more he bought me, the more my cheek burned
with a sense of annoyance and degradation.
As we re-entered the carriage, and I sat back feverish and fact,
I remembered what, in the hurry of events dark and bright, I had wholly forgotten.
The letter of my uncle, John heir, to Mrs. Reed,
his intention to adopt me and make me his legatee.
It would indeed be a relief, I thought, if I had ever so small an independency.
I never can bear being dressed like a doll by Mr. Rochester, or sitting like a second
dane with the golden shower falling daily round me.
I will write to Madera the moment I get home, and tell my uncle, John,
I am going to be married, and to whom, if I had but a prospect of one day,
bringing Mr. Rochester an accession of fortune,
I could better endure to be kept by him now.
And somewhat relieved by this idea, which I failed not to execute that day,
I ventured once more to meet my masters and lovers eye, which most pertenaciously
sought mine, though I averted both face and gaze.
He smiled.
And I thought his smile was such as a sultan might, in a blissful and fond
moment, bestow on a slave his gold and gems had enriched.
I crushed his hand, which was ever hunting mine, vigorously
and thrust it back to him red with a passionate pressure.
You need not look in that way, I said.
If you do, I'll wear nothing but my old lowwood frocks to the end of the chapter.
I'll be married in this lilac gingham.
You may make a dressing gown for yourself out of the Pearl Grey silk, and an
infinite series of waistcoats out of the black satin.
He chuckled.
He rubbed his hands.
Oh, it is rich to see and hear her.
He exclaimed.
Is she original?
Is she pecan?
I would not exchange this one little English girl for the Grand Turks' whole
saraglio, gazelle eyes, hoori forms and all.
The Eastern allusion bit me again.
I'll not stand you an inch in the stead of a saraglio,
I said, so don't consider me an equivalent for one.
If you have a fancy for anything in that line, away with you, sir, to the bazaars
of Stamble without delay, and lay out in extensive slave purchases some of that
spare cash you seem at a loss to spend satisfactorily here.
And what will you do, Janet, while I'm bargaining for so
many tons of flesh and such an assortment of black eyes?
I'll be preparing myself to go out as a missionary, to preach liberty to them that
are enslaved, your haram inmates amongst the rest.
I'll get admitted there, and I'll stir up mutiny,
and you, three-tailed Bashar as you are, sir.
Shall in a trice find yourself fettered amongst our hands, nor will I,
for one, consent to cut your bonds till you have signed a
charter, the most liberal that despot ever yet conferred.
I would consent to be at your mercy, Jane.
I would have no mercy, Mr. Rochester, if you
supplicated for it with an eye like that.
While you looked so, I should be certain that whatever charter you might grant
under coercion, your first act, when released, would be to violate its conditions.
Why, Jane, what would you have?
I fear you will compel me to go through a private
marriage ceremony, besides that performed at the altar.
You will stipulate, I see, for peculiar terms, what will they be?
I only want an easy mind, sir, not crushed by crowded obligations.
Do you remember what you said of Selin Varan,
of the diamonds, the cashmiers you gave her?
I will not be your English, Selin Varan.
I shall continue to act as Adele's governess.
By that, I shall earn my board and lodging and thirty pounds a year besides.
I'll furnish my own wardrobe out of that money, and you shall give me nothing but,
well, but what?
Your regard.
And if I give you mine in return, that debt will be quit.
Well, for cool native impudence and pure innate pride, you haven't your equal,
said he.
We were now approaching Thornfield.
Will it please you to dine with me today?
He asked, as we re-entered the gates.
No, thank you, sir.
And what for?
No, thank you, if one may inquire.
I never have dined with you, sir, and I see no reason why I should now,
till, till what, you delight in half -phrases, till I can't help it.
Do you suppose I eat like an ogre or a ghoul,
that you dread being the companion of my repast?
I have formed no supposition on the subject, sir,
but I want to go on as usual for another month.
You will give up your governessing slavery at once.
Indeed, begging your pardon, sir, I shall not.
I shall just go on with it as usual.
I shall keep out of your way all day, as I have been accustomed to do.
You may send for me in the evening, when you feel disposed to see me,
and I'll come then, but at no other time.
I want to smoke, Jane, or a pinch of snuff, to comfort me under all this,
pour me dawn a room condonce, as Adele would say, and unfortunately I have
neither my cigar case, nor my snuff box, but listen, whisper.
It is your time now, little tyrant, but it will be mine presently,
and when once I have fairly seized you, to have and to hold, I'll just
figuratively speaking, attach you to a chain like this, touching his watchguard.
Yes, bonnie-wee thing, I'll wear you in my bosom, lest my jewel I should tine.
He said this as he helped me to a light from the carriage, and while he afterwards
lifted out Adele, I entered the house and made good of my retreat upstairs.
He duly summoned me to his presence in the evening.
I had prepared a occupation for him, for I was determined
not to spend the whole time in a tet-a-tet conversation.
I remembered his fine voice.
I knew he liked to sing.
Good singers generally do.
I was no vocalist myself, and in his fastidious judgment, no musician either,
but I delighted in listening when the performance was good.
No sooner had twilight, that hour of romance began
to lower her blue and starry banner over the lattice.
Then I rose, opened the piano, and entreated
him for the love of heaven to give me a song.
He said I was a capricious witch, and that he would rather sing another time.
But I avert that no time was like the present.
Did I like his voice?
He asked very much.
I was not fond of pampering that susceptible vanity of his, but for once,
and from motives of expediency, I would ensoothe and stimulate it.
Then Jane, you must play the accompaniment.
Very well, sir, I will try.
I did try, but was presently swept off the stool and denominated a little bungler.
Being pushed unceremoniously to one side, which was precisely what I wished.
He usurped my place, and proceeded to accompany
himself, for he could play as well as sing.
I hide me to the window recess.
And while I sat there, and looked out on the still trees and dim lawn, to a sweet
air was sung in mellow tones the following strain.
The truest love that ever-heart felt at its kindled core, did through each vein,
in quicken start, the tide of being poor.
Her coming was my hope each day, her parting was my pain,
the chance that did her steps delay was ice in every vein.
I dreamed it would be nameless bliss, as I loved loved to be, and to this object
did I press, as blind as eagerly, but wide as
pathless was the space that lay our lives between.
And dangerous as the foamy race of ocean surges green, and haunted as a robber path
through wilderness or wood, for might and right
and woe and wrath, between our spirits stood.
I dangers dared, I hindrance scorned, the omens did defy, whatever menaced,
harassed, warned, I passed impetuous by, son sped my rainbow, fast as light,
I flew as in a dream, for glorious rows upon
my sight, that child of shower and gleam.
Still bright on clouds of suffering dim, shines that soft solemn joy, nor care I
now, how dense and grim disasters gather nigh.
I care not in this moment, sweet, though all I have rushed over,
should come on pinion, strong and fleet, proclaiming vengeance saw, though haughty
hate should strike me down, right bar approach to me, and grinding might,
with furious frown, swear endless enmity.
My love has placed her little hand with noble faith in mine, and vowed that
wedlock's sacred band, our nature shall entwine, my love has sworn with ceiling
kiss, with me to live, to die, I have at last my nameless bliss,
as I love, lover dem I.
He rose and came towards me, and I saw his face all kindled, and his full falcon eye
flashing, and tenderness and passion in every liniment, I quailed momentarily,
then I rallied.
Soft seen, daring demonstration I would not have, and I stood in peril of both,
a weapon of defense must be prepared.
I wetted my tongue, as he reached me, I asked
with a sparity, whom he was going to marry now.
That was a strange question to be put by his darling Jane.
Indeed, I considered it a very natural and necessary
one, he had talked of his future wife dying with him.
What did he mean by such a pagan idea?
I had no intention of dying with him, he might depend on that.
Oh, all he longed, all he prayed for was that I
might live with him, death was not for such as I.
Indeed it was, I had as good a right to die when my time came as he had,
but I should bide that time and not be hurried away in a suttie.
Would I forgive him for the selfish idea and prove my pardon by a reconciling kiss?
No, I would rather be excused.
Here I heard myself apostrophized as a hard little thing, and it was added,
any other woman would have been melted to marrow
at hearing such stanzas crooned in her praise.
I assured him I was naturally hard, very flinty, and that he would often find me so.
And that moreover, I was determined to show him divers rugged points in my
character before the ensuing four weeks elapsed.
He should know fully what sort of a bargain he
had made, while there was yet time to rescind it.
Would I be quiet and talk rationally?
I would be quiet if he liked, and as to talking
rationally, I flattered myself I was doing that now.
He fretted, pished and pshored.
Very good, I thought.
You may fume and fidget as you please, but this
is the best plan to pursue with you, I am certain.
I like you more than I can say, but I'll not sink into a bathos of
sentiment, and with this needle of repartee
I'll keep you from the edge of the gulf too.
And moreover, maintained by its pungent aid, that distance between you and myself
most conducive to our real mutual advantage.
From less to more, I worked him up to considerable irritation.
Then, after he had retired in Dungeon, quite to the other end of the room,
I got up and saying, I wish you good night, sir.
In my natural and wanted respectful manner,
I slipped out by the side door and got away.
The system thus entered on, I pursued during the whole season of probation,
and with the best success.
He was kept, to be sure, rather cross and crusty.
But on the whole, I could see he was excellently entertained, and that a lamb
-like submission and turtle-dove sensibility, while fostering his despotism
more, would have pleased his judgment, satisfied
his common sense, and even suited his taste less.
In other people's presence, I was, as formerly, deferential and quiet,
any other line of conduct being uncalled for.
It was only in the evening conferences I thus thwarted and afflicted him.
He continued to send for me punctually, the moment the clock struck seven.
Though when I appeared before him now, he had no
such honeyed terms as love and darling on his lips.
The best words at my service were, provoking puppet, malicious elf,
sprite, changeling, etc.
For caresses, too, I now got grimaces, for a pressure of the hand, a pinch on the
arm, for a kiss on the cheek, a severe tweak of the ear.
It was all right.
At present, I decidedly preferred these fierce favors to anything more tender.
Mrs Fairfax, I saw, approved me.
Her anxiety on my account vanished, therefore I was certain I did well.
Meantime, Mr. Rochester affirmed I was wearing him to skin and bone, and
threatened awful vengeance for my present conduct at some period fast-coming.
I laughed in my sleeve at his menaces.
I can keep you in reasonable check now, I reflected,
and I don't doubt to be able to do it hereafter.
If one expedient loses its virtue, another must be devised.
Yet after all, my task was not an easy one.
Often, I would rather have pleased than teased him.
My future husband was becoming to me, my whole world, and more than the world,
almost my hope of heaven.
He stood between me and every thought of religion, as
an eclipse intervenes between man and the broad sun.
I could not, in those days, see God for his creature of whom I had made an idol.